War Council
Connecticut State Library
War Council records
1940-1945
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. War Council
9999 cubic feet
After war broke out in Europe in 1939, the State created the State Defense Council, similar to the one during the First World War. It coordinated domestic mobilization through advisory committees of leading citizens, local councils and public officials, and agencies of the U.S. government. By 1943, this body was known as the War Council. It went out of business on October 1, 1945.
RG050
Multiple
Historical Note
The World War II civilian effort in Connecticut was organized and corrdinated by the War Council, a small agency of the State Government, assisted by an appointed Council and various advisory committees of leading citizens, and working through local councils and public officials and in close collaboration with various United States Government agencies.
The War Council had its origin in the State Defense Council that was created by Governor Raymond E. Baldwin in June 1940. A council of nine civilians was appointed, and the Governor's Defense Cabinet, made up of State officials, was organized. From the two groups, a seven-member Joint Executive Defense Committee was established, headed by Col. Sanford H. Wadhams. On April 27, 1941, the General Assembly passed House Bill No. 6, setting up a new Defense Council to super cede the old dual structure. Samuel H. Fisher was appointed Administrator of Defense. He was succeeded on September 14, 1942, by Professor Wesley A. Sturges.
In February and March 1943, new acts were passed by the General Assembly, changing the name of the agency to War Council and somewhat increasing its scope and authority. There was, however, relatively little change in the program or structure of the Council. Edward J. Hickey served as Acting Administrator of the War Council from April 15 to July 12, 1943, and Harold F. Woodcock was Administrator until April 1, 1944. Mr. Henry B. Mosle held the office until the agency was terminated on October 1, 1945.
Scope and Content
Records include minutes, directives and circulars, general files, surveys, publications, and files (correspondence, memoranda, reports, subject files, and lists) documenting the work of sections dealing with protection services, an air raid network, air raid wardens, blackouts, bomb reconnaissance, communications, fire and plant protection, training, fuel, food, manpower, radio, film and statewide evacuation
Related Material
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The archives of the War Council appear to have been transferred to the Connecticut State Library immediately after the close of its work. An "Inventory" found in the Library files is dated July 1946; it seems to have been prepared by a War Council staff member, but the records were presumably already in Library custody. The files were moved about somewhat during subsequent years, but little seems to have been lost. In the course of recent study, appraisal and processing, substantial quantities were discarded. The records descrived in Items 39-42 were probably never in the custody of the War Council. They presumably were acquired by the State Library directly from the agencies concerned, but they are listed here because those agencies were a part of the War Council system.
Container List
- Records, 1940-1945
  - 1946-001
    - 1. Minutes of meetings, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
      Minutes of the Joint Executive Committee, the State Defense Council, the War Council and its committees.
      Container list located in box.
      - Minutes of the meeting of the Connecticut War Council, held in the Old Senate Chamber in the State Capitol, 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
      - Minutes of the meeting of the Connecticut War Council held in the Old Senate Chamber in the State Capitol, 1943 June 26 (Box 1)
      - Connecicut War Council (Box 1)
        - 1943 July 17, 2 copies (Box 1)
        - 1943 August 21, 2 copies (Box 1)
        - 1943 September 18, 2 copies (Box 1)
        - 1943 October 16, 2 copies (Box 1)
        - 1943 November 20, 2 copies (Box 1)